Okay, endocrine pathology.
So we're going to begin with the pituitary gland.
Of course, the pituitary gland is really divided
into an anterior and a posterior pituitary gland.
We're going to start with the anterior,
and then we'll move to the posterior
at the very end of this video.
So let's begin with pituitary adenoma.
This is a benign tumor of the anterior pituitary cells.
Of course, the anterior pituitary cells,
they produce a number of different hormones.
If the tumor produces hormones, we call that functional.
And if the tumor does not produce hormones,
we call that non-functional.
Now, if the tumor is non-functional,
then it will present with mass effect.
And one of the classic presentations would be,
for example, bitemporal hemianopsia.
Now, recall that the pituitary sits in the cella tersica,
and that adjacent to the cella tersica is the optic chiasm.
And so if the tumor was to press on the optic chiasm,
this would result in bitemporal hemianopsia,
or loss of peripheral vision in both eyes.
Just illustrating this, if this is the two eyes here,
and let's pretend they're looking at the numbers
one, two, and three, and four here.
And when you see the number one,
it actually crosses over and then comes like this,
and then crosses over the nerve like that.
When you would look at the number four,
it would come across like this,
and then, again, would come down the nerve
and cross like that.
When you look at the number two,
that would cross over here and come down like this.
And when you look at the number three,
Now, this here is the optic chiasm.
So imagine that if you've got a tumor
compressing the optic chiasm here,
you're going to lose the ability to see number 1, and you're going to lose the ability to see number 4.
And so here you can see that both eyes have lost their peripheral vision, and that's called bitemporal hemianoptia.
Now notice that the number 2 never ran through the optic chiasm, and this field also never ran through the optic chiasm.
Another complication could be hypopituitarism.
If you have a tumor and it begins to compress the normal pituitary, then you will see signs and symptoms of loss of the hormones that are normally produced by the pituitary,
and that's called hypopituitarism.
And finally, a non-functional tumor could also present with headache.
Now functioning tumors are going to present with features based on the hormone produced.
Recall that the anterior pituitary produces a bunch of hormones, and theoretically, a functional tumor could produce any of these hormones.
However, the most commonly produced hormone is prolactin, and hence the most common type of pituitary adenoma is a prolactinoma.
Now when you have a prolactinoma, it's going to result in signs and symptoms based on the production of prolactin,
and you're well aware of the fact that prolactin is important in the production of milk by the breast, and so you'll get galactorrhea.
And in addition, recall that prolactin inhibits GnRH synthesis and release.
Now if you don't have GnRH synthesis and release, you're not going to get FSH and LH release,
and therefore if you don't get FSH and LH release, that's going to result in amenorrhea in females.
So these are the two key findings in females.
In males, a prolactinoma would result in decreased libido.
Again, prolactin would inhibit GnRH release, which would then reduce the release of FSH and LH,
and so that would result in decreased libido in the male.
And at the same time, there could be headache due to mass effect.
Now it's important to note that males will not get galactorrhea,
and that's because males don't have sufficient breast tissue for milk production.
Recall that the functional unit of the breast is called the terminal duct lobular unit.
Here's the terminal duct, and here's the lobular unit.
Remember that the lobules contain these glands, which basically produce milk.
Now this lobular unit would develop in a female after puberty.
However, males do not have lobular units in their breast.
They simply have terminal ducts.
And so because there's only a terminal duct, there's no ability to produce milk.
And so again, a male would not develop galactorrhea.
Now the treatment of prolactinoma is dopamine agonist.
Remember that dopamine from the hypothalamus normally inhibits prolactin secretion.
And so if you give a dopamine agonist, you would also be able to inhibit prolactin secretion,
and actually the tumor would shrink.
And so for example, bromocryptine would be a useful dopamine agonist.
In addition, you could also remove the tumor by a surgery.
The next step of adenoma is a growth hormone adenoma.
Of course, this tumor would release growth hormone.
If this tumor were to arise in children, it would result in gigantism.
And that's because children have not yet fused their epiphyseal growth plate.
And so they would get linear growth of bone in response to the excess growth hormone.
Adults develop acromegaly.
And acromegaly refers to an enlargement of the bones of the hands, feet, and jaw.
In addition, they could grow the visceral organs, for example, the heart.
In fact, cardiac failure is the most common cause of death in these patients.
They can also develop an enlarged tongue.
An important high yield association here is that growth hormone adenoma is often associated with secondary diabetes.
Recall from physiology that growth hormone decreases glucose uptake into cells.
And so, therefore, if there's a lot of growth hormone around, glucose will not be taken up by cells.
And secondary diabetes will develop.
The diagnosis of growth hormone adenoma is made by looking at elevated growth hormone levels
and elevated insulin-like growth factor levels.
Recall that one of the effects of growth hormone is to go to the liver
and cause increased production of insulin-like growth factor.
And it's actually the insulin-like growth factor that mediates the growth of tissues.
And so, therefore, you would expect insulin-like growth factor to be elevated.
Were you to give a patient oral glucose, normally you should be able to suppress growth hormone release.
However, oral glucose would not be able to suppress growth hormone if there was a growth hormone adenoma.
A potential treatment is octreotide.
This is particularly high yield.
Recall that growth hormone-releasing hormone actually goes to the anterior pituitary.
And in response to growth hormone-releasing hormone, the anterior pituitary then will secrete growth hormone.
The way by which octreotide works is that it is a somatostatin analog,
and it blocks the response of the anterior pituitary cell to growth hormone-releasing hormone.
And so, therefore, you would not be able to generate the production of growth hormone.
You could also give growth hormone receptor antagonists to block the effect of growth hormone,
or, of course, surgery could be performed to remove the tumor.
Other types of functional adenoma include ACTH cell adenomas.
They would secrete ACTH resulting in Cushing syndrome.
We'll cover this in more detail when we talk about Cushing syndrome in a later section in this chapter.
Of course, there can be a TSH cell adenoma, an LH-producing adenoma, and an FSH-producing adenoma.
However, these are rare, and so we won't go into more detail here.
Now, shifting gears a little bit, moving to hypopituitarism.
This is where you have insufficient production of hormones by the anterior pituitary.
Symptoms usually don't arise until you've lost greater than 75% of the pituitary parenchyma.
Causes include pituitary adenoma.
That would be a common cause in adults.
The idea here is that the pituitary adenoma would grow,
and it would compress the normal pituitary,
which would then cause loss of the tissue of the pituitary.
Another possibility with a pituitary adenoma is that you could get bleeding into the adenoma.
That's called epoplexy, and when you get bleeding into the adenoma,
the adenoma would rapidly grow and would compress the normal tissue.
An additional mechanism of hypopituitarism would be a cranial pharyngioma in children.
Again, the same thing.
The cranial pharyngioma, which we'll cover when we do CNS,
normally arises within the region of the cellotersica,
and so it could compress the normal pituitary tissue.
Sheehan syndrome is particularly interesting and particularly high yield.
Recall that during pregnancy, there's a high demand of hormone.
Due to the physiology of the pregnancy,
and so the pituitary gland actually doubles in size.
However, although the gland doubles in size,
the blood supply does not increase that much.
And so therefore, that leaves the pituitary relatively susceptible to infarction.
Now imagine that if a woman gives birth and loses a tremendous amount of blood,
it would be very easy for the pituitary to undergo infarction,
and that's called Sheehan syndrome.
Now what's interesting about Sheehan syndrome and what's high yield for board examinations
is that these patients present with poor lactation and loss of pubic hair.
Loss of pubic hair is a very important association with loss of pituitary function,
and that's because pubic hair is dependent on androgens,
and those androgens would arise due to LH, which arises from the anterior pituitary.
So again, Sheehan syndrome is particularly high yield.
Empty cellos syndrome refers to a circumstance in which the cello is empty and the pituitary is missing.
It can occur in two ways.
It can occur due to secondary trauma to the pituitary,
in which case the pituitary would be damaged,
or it can occur in a primary circumstance where there is a congenital defect of the cella,
such that you get herniation of the arachnoid and the CSF into the cella,
which then compresses and destroys the pituitary.
Again, the idea here is that if this is the cella with the pituitary sitting in it,
recall that attached to the cella here, the bone of the cella is going to be the dura,
and then there's going to be the arachnoid here as a second layer,
and then, of course, you've got the pituitary sitting here,
and attached directly to the pituitary would be the pia.
Now, if there was herniation of arachnoid and CSF into the cella,
that would compress the normal pituitary,
and as it compressed the normal pituitary, the pituitary would then be destroyed,
resulting in something called empty cella syndrome.
Moving on to the posterior pituitary, recall that there are two hormones
that are released by the posterior pituitary.
The first is antidiuretic hormone, or ADH, and the second is oxytocin.
Now, interestingly, neither of these are actually made in the posterior pituitary.
Both are made in the hypothalamus and then transmitted via axons
to the posterior pituitary for eventual release.
Of course, recall from physiology that the role of ADH is to regulate free water
at the distal tubules and the collecting ducts.
So, essentially, it controls the movement of free water.
And oxytocin mediates uterine contractions and the release of breast milk
during the suckling response.
The first disorder is central diabetes insipidus.
Remember that the word diabetes refers to the fact that someone is urinating too much,
and the reason that they're urinating too much is because they have an ADH deficiency.
Now, I mean, just listen to the words, antidiuretic hormone.
So, when you have antidiuretic hormone, you will not diurese, you will not urinate.
However, if you're lacking antidiuretic hormone, then you will diurese,
and you'll get diabetes, which is to urinate too much.
Now, this can be due to hypothalamic pathology because, again, ADH is produced in the hypothalamus,
or it could be due to posterior pituitary pathology because, again, ADH is released by the posterior pituitary.
Some examples of pathology include tumor, trauma, infection, inflammation, etc.
Now, the clinical features will be based on the fact that there is a lack of antidiuretic hormone,
so the patient is diuresing too much.
They're urinating too much.
And so they'll have polyuria.
And in response to that polyuria, they're going to have to drink a lot,
and so they'll also have polydipsia, which means that they're drinking a lot.
Now, the patients will, again, lose a lot of free water because ADH regulates free water.
And so they're going to end up concentrating the sodium in the blood, which is going to give them hypernatremia,
and they're also going to concentrate the serum, giving them a high serum osmolality.
Of course, they're losing a ton of free water, so they'll have a low osmolality.
It will be a very dilute urine, and it'll have a low specific gravity.
Diagnosis is made by the water deprivation test.
If you force a person to not drink, that should result in dehydration,
which would then result in concentration of the urine.
However, they're not able to concentrate the urine because they have too much antidiuretic hormone,
and so, therefore, they will not be able to increase the urine osmolality,
i.e., they will not be able to concentrate the urine.
The treatment would be to give ADH, and so you can give desmopressin,
which is an ADH analog, which would then reverse the symptoms.
In nephrogenic diabetes insipidus, the patients, again, are urinating too much.
The problem this time, however, is not in the brain, but instead it's in the kidney,
and so they call that nephrogenic diabetes insipidus,
and that's because the kidney is not responding to antidiuretic hormone.
This is usually due to inherited mutations or drugs.
Some classic drugs that can cause this include lithium and demeclocycline,
which is an antibiotic that is not used so much anymore.
The symptoms will be similar to central diabetes insipidus.
However, there will be no response to desmopressin,
so you give desmopressin, which is that ADH analog,
and there is no response, and that's because the kidney cannot respond to ADH.
The syndrome of inappropriate ADH secretion, or SIADH,
is when you have excessive ADH secretion.
The clinical features will be based on having too much antidiuretic hormone,
so if you have too much antidiuretic hormone, you're not going to diurese.
You're going to end up holding free water,
and so therefore the patients get hyponatremia because they dilute out their sodium,
and in addition, they get a low serum osmolality.
Patients can also develop mental status change and seizures,
and that's because when you have hyponatremia,
that leads to swelling of the nerves and cerebral edema,
which then leads to mental status changes and seizures.
The causes include ectopic production,
one of the classic associations, a small cell carcinoma of the lung.
Recall that it can produce antidiuretic hormone,
giving you a syndrome of inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion.
A CNS trauma can also do this.
Pulmonary infection, in fact, pulmonary pathology generally can do this.
For example, patients with COPD can have this.
In addition, patients with pulmonary infection can have this.
And then some drugs, for example, cyclophosphamide,
can also result in inappropriate antidiuretic hormone secretion.
The treatment is free water restriction, or dameclacycline.
Again, dameclacycline will block the effect of antidiuretic hormone.
And that concludes this section on the pituitary gland.